so this
this is the simile of wet
wood wet timber
suppose there were a wet sappy piece of
timber lying in the water and a man were to
lying in the water and a man were to
come along with the upper fire stick
thinking i'll light a fire i'll produce
heat now what do you think would he be able
now what do you think would he be able
to light a fire and produce heat by
rubbing the upper fire stick in the wet
sappy timber lying in the wood
no master gotoma why is that because the
timber is wet
and besides it is laying in the water
eventually the man would reap
only his share of weariness and
disappointment and buddha says so it is with
and buddha says so it is with
contemplatives
who do not live withdrawn from
sensuality in body and mind and whose desire
in body and mind and whose desire
infatuation and fever for sensuality is
not relinquished and stilled within him
whether or not he feels painful wrecking
piercing feelings
due to his striving for awakening
he is incapable of knowledge and vision
and self-awakening
so no matter how
intense many different virtues you keep
or
and how painful it is how sensuous
strange you are
if you're struggling if you're not if
you're not devaluing the centrality if
you're still valuing it holding on to it
as a valuable thing if you're not seeing
the danger from in it
means you're still with that centrality
even if you're not engaging in it if
you're just torturing yourself
not eating maybe like not just drinking
water and so on
you're still doing that with centrality
okay so that's right yeah doesn't matter
the extent of that endurance it will not
um result in wisdom as you said
previously with you can be
with you can be
secluded from music and
lovely food or whatever and people
and be in an empty room but you're
delighting in the prospect that once you
leave this room you're gonna
yeah you know you're gonna taste this
like lovely food and you're gonna see
some some people whatever and that's
some people whatever and that's
so you will never get uh yeah so then
your your
your uh your abstinence is is temporary
means overall framework of sensuality
remains you're not relinquishing
that you might be playing with it and
restraining restraining yourself for whatever reason
restraining yourself for whatever reason
but overall the value of centrality
remains unchanged
so that's what i mean when i said in the
before like
when you do keep the virtue
and practice sense restraint and have
this enduring you have to do it with the
attitude or i will do this infinitely
forever it doesn't matter how long this lasts i
it doesn't matter how long this lasts i
will have to do it forever not like
i'll do this for a week and then what oh
then i'll most likely go back to the
same value of central and chasing
pleasure that's why you're not free not because
that's why you're not free not because
you haven't endured enough you might
have already endured more than enough
for wisdom to arise
but the wisdom won't arise because
overall you're not relinquishing
the value of centrality not because you
haven't endured sufficiently
yeah it's just i'll just continue with
this simulation
it says uh suppose there were a wet
sappy piece of
timber lying on the land far from the
water and a man were to come along with
an upper fire stick thinking i'll light
that fire
and produce heat would he be able to
light a fire and produce heat by rubbing
that upper stick
up of a fire stick with the wet sappy
timber lying on land
far from water so no why is that because
the timber is wet
and sappy even though it is lying on
land hmm does it dried up that's exactly
what you just said yeah
even though you are yeah you're not in
the water anymore yeah
but the mind's still wet with the value
of centrality
it doesn't matter what you're doing how
much effort you're putting
how emotional is for how many hours you
sit in your samadhi
if you have not on the level of your
views devalued sensuality forever
devalued sensuality forever
you are still within it so there will be
no wisdom arising on account of whatever
practice you do
yeah it keeps giving so the third
part of the seminary suppose there were
dry sapless
piece of timber lying on land far from
water and a man were to come along with
upper fire stick
thinking i'll light that fire and
produce heat would he be able to produce
that heat
yes master belt because that timber is
dry and sapless
and it is lying on the land far and
you'll probably be able to do it with
little effort
because the effort is pretty much
determine how good how wet the wood is
determines how much
how hard you have to rub the sticks are
drying yeah if it's damp
still you have to you have to do it even
harder and so on but if it's really
really dry
so if you actually invest your effort in
drying the sticks
then it's going to take very little
physical effort to light the fire with
it
so that's what i mean often like we
often repeat that doesn't matter whether
you're a monk
or a lay person if you want to practice
the dhamma
practically speaking most of the work
comes down to drying your mind from
sensuality it doesn't come down to finding a
it doesn't come down to finding a
perfect technique or reading the exact
suit they'll make you lighter
and the reason why you're not
enlightened even after you read all the
sutas it's not because
you haven't read enough sutas or you
haven't thought about them enough it's
because your sticks were not dry enough and it's
your sticks were not dry enough and it's
always
and again it's not it's not um
accidental that that's always that
something which is being overlooked
that's the that's why sensuality is hard
to get rid of because it's easy to
overlook it
so sense restraint is already the
practice of dhamma
virtue is already the practice of dhamma
because you're already drawing the
sticks and that's by the way if sometimes
and that's by the way if sometimes
people wonder you know you read a sudden
and you and a man is mentioned that he
just heard one sentence from the buddha
and became enlightened and people just
assumed oh he was so lucky with their special
oh he was so lucky with their special
powers made him enlightened no they
would have said himself i cannot make
anyone enlighten i point to the way
they either choose to follow it or not
that's it
all tataria that can do is point the way
so how did then that man get enlightened
after one sentence then you realize if
you actually
read closer or read other suitors oh
yeah his mind was very dry
he spent years of quite the secluded
practice withdrawn from
centrality obviously devaluing
sensuality thoroughly
because otherwise one sentence from the
buddha would have not been enough for
enlightenment
so now when you read thousands the
sentences thousands of sentences from
the buddha and you're not enlightened
it's not because you haven't you read
them wrongly or because they're
different sentences
it's because your sticks are wet
you can't light fire because you're not
withdrawn from centrality
so that's when practically speaking most
of the work especially for a lay person
who wants to practice them
without becoming a monk is about
withdrawing from centrality in the lay
world which is doable does mean easy or
which is doable does mean easy or
pleasant but doable
but the worst possible thing to do is to
tell oh you don't have to withdraw from
oh you don't have to withdraw from
sensuality and you can practice
for the fire that the buddha says it's
impossible for as long as you don't dry the sticks
for as long as you don't dry the sticks
just keep practicing and sticks will
magically become dry
and the fire of wisdom will arise and we
will all be happy
it doesn't work for that and it works
the opposite as the word described
all the effort you're going to put in
light in the fire with wet sticks
will go to waste because you haven't you
have not dried the sticks
and you will only reap despair and
frustration i wish
i wish
so withdrawal from centrality sustaining
the mind we draw from centrality
it's not just doable it's what the
practice is
becoming immovable in the garden and
then you you might be
one of those people that needed only one
sentence for the right view and enlightenment
for the right view and enlightenment
because you did the actual work of
drying your sticks from centrality
you've done eighty percent of the work
already yeah but most people
would be coming to the dhamma to
practice it with genuine reasons
with serious determination but at the
same time
still not completely devaluing that
centrality still thinking that they don't need to
still thinking that they don't need to
devalue sensuality
oh but i don't have to because i'm not a
monk or something like that
and that's why all the effort and all
determination they have
will not result in wisdom
and all you need to do is read a suta
like that and it just
says it clearly this is the necessary
prerequisite and then you realize if you complete
and then you realize if you complete
that prerequisite
of living withdrawal from sensuality you
will need very little effort
as it says it says so it is with
contemplatives who live withdrawn from
sensuality in body and mind
and whose desire infatuation and fever
for sensuality is relinquished
instilled within him whether or not he
feels painful piercing he's driving he doesn't
painful piercing he's driving he doesn't
matter he's capable of knowledge and
vision and self-awakening he doesn't matter
and self-awakening he doesn't matter
that's where the work is yeah
it always comes to mind that i forgot
the name of that layman in the sutta
he was obviously practicing down before
and i think multiple times he's seen the
buddha and uh and eventually he even was was
and uh and eventually he even was was
freeing himself from sensuality
and went back home and said to his wives
that it's unsuitable for me to engage in
it's unsuitable for me to engage in
sexual intercourse with you now
so he's not becoming a monk or anything
like that so
but you know i did take you on as my
wife's i promise to look after you so i
will so any of you wants to stay or get
so any of you wants to stay or get
remarried let me know i'll arrange
everything otherwise i'll look after you for the
otherwise i'll look after you for the
rest of my life
but i'll be celibate i cannot not be
celibate it's not suitable for me to not
be celibate
having understood the dharma to the
extent i did
so he took on that as a normal behavior
because you know
that's where the work is abstaining from
sensuality keeping the sticks dry that that is
keeping the sticks dry that that is
resulting in wisdom
and that's what i mean even the little
instruction from the sutta let alone all
the dipitakas we have now
in in 15 different translations and
original polis and everything else
oh if your sticks are dry you need maybe
of that and you will start seeing things
clearly it's impossible not to
because you are actually doing the work
on the level that it matters
but as i said when we when we started
this sensuality that's like
a mentally abandoning centrality it's
not like i don't think about it
means devaluing it means you step out
you step
physically outside of the puddle of
centrality the lake the swamp of centrality but
the lake the swamp of centrality but
mentally
you still value that water so mentally
you're not withdrawn from it
so you might be living on top of a
mountain secluded from from central
distractions but mentally you still value pleasure of
but mentally you still value pleasure of
the senses you don't see the peril
infinitely forever you don't see that
that's why mentally you are not
withdrawn from it
but if you start contemplating the
infinite peril
mentally let alone physically you are
withdrawing yourself mentally as well
and then things for the suttas will just
start falling into place
much more than before
and then you just do one rub and there
is already smoke
and fire started because you dry the
steaks properly
so what i'm trying to have to point out
is that
because people you know it's it's
obviously it's subtle subtle things so
people can easily misunderstand
what mental withdrawal from sensuality
is it's not just i will never think
these central thoughts
they might present themselves it's
whether you value delight entertain
indulge them mentally do you see the
danger by seeing the danger automatically you
by seeing the danger automatically you
you're making yourself withdraw
from those values from those thoughts
are you withdrawn no means you're not
seeing the danger
but you can't decide i will mentally
withdraw myself from it
because that mind is already in it
but you can make your mind withdraw
yourself from it by seeing the danger
in that which it values
and you will never see the danger in
that which you value
if you think you don't have to do it
if you think you're exempted from it if
you think centrality is not a problem
if you think centrality is not your
problem if you think because you're not
a monk you don't need to address these
things well you want to purchase the demo it
well you want to purchase the demo it
doesn't matter where you're mounting
the sticks need to be dry